The general budget of the country has been presented but the confusion of the
people investing in the stock market has
probably not been cleared yet. In such a situation,
due to the tax related changes in this budget, people are a bit confused
and moreover, the season of ITR filing is
also going on, in such a situation, people are confused as to
how much tax do we have to pay on the earnings made in the stock market. Well,
hello and namaskar, I am Riya and
in today's video, I am going to answer this question of yours. First of all, let us
know
what the income tax rule says.
If seen in the context of income tax, then the
income of any person has been
divided into five categories. First is
income from salary, second is income from house property,
third is
income from business or profession, fourth is income from capital gains
and fifth is income from any other source.
Now let us know in
which category your earnings from the stock market have been
kept
[Music]
If you invest money in the stock market, then
your earnings are taxed either on capital  Will it be
taxed under gains or under other sources?
If you earn money by buying and selling shares, then it will be
considered as capital gains,
whereas income from dividends
comes under the category of other sources.
Now if we talk about capital gains, then there are
two types of them, first is long term
capital gain which happens when you
sell a share after at least 1 year. Till now
you used to get exemption on income tax up to ₹1 lakh on this,
which has been increased in this budget.  25
lakh. Income above this limit was
previously taxed at 10%,
which has been increased to 12.5% ​​in this budget.
Second, short-term capital gains, which occurs
when you sell shares within one year,
previously
attracting a flat tax of 15%, but now it has been
increased to 20%.
Changes to the capital gains tax in this budget have been made
for only a few financial assets, the
full details of which have not yet been revealed.
It is believed that earnings from the stock market will
also be included in the same category.
If you earn intraday
or receive dividends, your
earnings will be counted as income from other sources.
You will be taxed on this income according to the applicable tax rate.
However, if your dividend
exceeds ₹1,000, a % tax will be levied on it by the broker or
mutual fund company.
If you
invest in the stock market while working, you will need to
file your ITR.  You will definitely need these five documents: the
first is
Form 16, the second is Form 26S, the third is
Annual Information Statement (AIS), the
fourth is Capital Gain Statement, and the fifth is
Tax Profit and Loss Statement. Well, that's all
for today. I hope you got
answers to all your questions in this video. Keep
watching Business to stay updated with all the news related to finance and market.